<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[D3 visualizations, Underscore mixins, etc.]]></title>
  <link href="http://Sigfried.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Sigfried.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-17T15:49:49-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://Sigfried.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sigfried Gold]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Supergroup]]></title>
    <link href="http://Sigfried.github.io/blog/supergroup/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-27T00:07:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://Sigfried.github.io/blog/supergroup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<script src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/underscore.js/1.8.2/underscore.js"></script>


<script src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/d3/3.5.5/d3.js"></script>


<script src="https://rawgit.com/Sigfried/supergroup/master/supergroup.js"></script>


<script src="http://Sigfried.github.io/supergroup/examples_gist/prism.js"></script>


<!-- more -->




<p>Supergroup brings extreme convenience and understandability to the manipulation of
Javascript data collections, especially in the context of D3.js visualization
programming.</p>




<p>Certain data manipulation problems arise over and over again in
data-centric Javascript programming.
<a href="https://github.com/mbostock/d3/wiki/Arrays#-nest">d3.nest</a>,
<a href="https://github.com/mbostock/d3/wiki/Arrays#associative-arrays">d3.map</a>,
and <a href="http://underscorejs.org/#groupBy">Underscore.groupBy</a>
(<a href="https://github.com/iros/underscore.nest">Underscore.Nest</a> for
multi-level groups) solve the most completely generic aspects of
these problems, but after using these generic tools, there is
often much work left to do to extract the desired information
from the resulting data structures.  In most cases where you
might use one of these generic utility functions, Supergroup will
save you some of that further work.</p>


<p>Just to be clear about the problem&mdash;you start with tabular data from a CSV
file, a SQL query, or some AJAX call:</p>

<p><span class="iframe">Some very fake hospital data in a CSV file&#8230;</span>
<iframe width="100%" height="70px" src="http://Sigfried.github.io/supergroup/examples_gist/examples.html?data">
</iframe></p>




<p><span class="iframe">&#8230;turned into canonical array of Objects (using d3.csv, for instance)</span>
<iframe width="100%" height="80px" src="http://Sigfried.github.io/supergroup/examples_gist/examples.html?json">
</iframe></p>


<p>You group the records on the values of one or more fields with a standard
grouping function, giving you data like:</p>

<p><span class="iframe">d3.nest().key(function(d) { return d.Physician; }).key(function(d) { return d.Unit; }).map(data)</span>
<iframe width="100%" height="150px" src="http://Sigfried.github.io/supergroup/examples_gist/examples.html?d3map">
</iframe></p>


<p><span class="iframe">d3.nest().key(function(d) { return d.Physician; }).key(function(d) { return d.Unit; }).entries(data)</span>
<iframe width="100%" height="150px" src="http://Sigfried.github.io/supergroup/examples_gist/examples.html?d3nest">
</iframe></p>


<p>To my mind, these are awkward data structures (not to mention the awkwardness
of the calling functions.) The <code>map</code> version looks ok in the console, but
D3 wants data in arrays, not as objects. The <code>entries</code> version gives us
arrays of key/value pairs, but on upper levels <code>values</code> is another array of
key/value pairs while on the bottom level <code>values</code> is an array of records. In
both <code>entries</code> and <code>map</code>, you can&rsquo;t tell from a node at any level what
dimension was being grouped at that level.</p>

<p>Supergroup gives you almost everything you&rsquo;d want for every item in your nest
(or in your single array if you have a one-level grouping):</p>

<ul>
<li>An array of the values grouped on (could be strings, numbers, or dates) (<a href="#sgphysunit">example</a>)</li>
<li>The records associated with each group (<a href="#records">example</a>)</li>
<li>Information about the values at any level

<ul>
<li>Parent group if any</li>
<li>Immediate child groups if any</li>
<li>All descendant groups</li>
<li>Only descendant groups at the leaf level</li>
<li>Aggregate calculations on records for that group and its descendants</li>
<li>Path of group names from root to current group</li>
<li>Path of group dimension names from root to current group</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Information about the groupings at any level</li>
<li>For a group at any level, the name of the dimension (attribute, column, property, etc.) grouped on</li>
<li>Any of these in a format D3 or some other tool expects</li>
</ul>


<h2>Supergroup</h2>

<p>  Works as an Underscore (or Lo-Dash) mixin:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>&lt;script src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/underscore.js/1.8.2/underscore.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</span><span class='line'>&lt;script src="https://rawgit.com/Sigfried/supergroup/master/supergroup.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</span><span class='line'>&lt;script&gt;
</span><span class='line'>    var sg = _.supergroup(data, dimension_name)  // single-level grouping
</span><span class='line'>    var sg = _.supergroup(data, [dim1, dim2])  // multi-level grouping
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/script&gt;</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Lists and Values</h2>

<p>  <code>_.supergroup</code> returns an array of String or Number objects (Dates not yet
  implemented). Array elements represent the values grouped by. These Value
  objects are loaded with lots of juicy properties and methods.</p>

<p>  In the example below we group by Physician and Unit. So <code>_.supergroup</code>
  returns a list of physicians.  The first item in this list, <code>sg[0]</code>,
  &ldquo;Adams&rdquo;, is a String object. <code>sg[0].records</code> is an array containing the
  subset of original records where Physician=&ldquo;Adams&rdquo;.  <code>sg[0].children</code>
  is another list of Strings. These are all the unique Units for records belonging
  to Adams. <code>sg[0].children[0].records</code> (not shown) would be the subset of
  records where Physician=&ldquo;Adams&rdquo; and Unit=&ldquo;preop&rdquo;.</p>

<p>  <a id='sgphysunit'></a>
  <p><span class="iframe">Supergroup on physician and unit</span>
  <iframe width="100%" height="400px" src="http://Sigfried.github.io/supergroup/examples_gist/examples.html?sgphysunit">
  </iframe></p></p>

<p>  It does a bunch more that I still need to document.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TreeLike CSV Data Browser]]></title>
    <link href="http://Sigfried.github.io/blog/treelike/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-27T00:06:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://Sigfried.github.io/blog/treelike</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>TreeLike is an experimental tool allowing rapid exploration
of the contents and inter-relationships across the columns of spreadsheet or
CSV data. Use it to load any local CSV file.
It immediately shows the distributions of values in all columns, and by
laying out the columns in some nesting order, can show hierarchical
relationships between values across columns. When two columns have a
many-to-many relationship, the merge feature shows connections in both
directions, not just from parent to child. And parent/child
relationships can be reordered with one or two mouse clicks.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><a href="../treelike/demo.html">Demo</a> (you&rsquo;ll need a data file, how about: <a href="https://raw.github.com/Sigfried/treelike/master/data/mysql_world_data.csv">MySQL world data</a>)</p>

<p>To understand what it does, you need to see it in action. This rough
demo video will explain:</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://Sigfried.github.io//www.youtube.com/embed/mJ8ljG8qpZk" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>TreeLike will be most helpful with files of between about 4 and
20 columns. It should be fine with at least tens of thousands of rows,
but it hasn&rsquo;t been well tested.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sequence-viz]]></title>
    <link href="http://Sigfried.github.io/blog/sequence-viz/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-27T00:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://Sigfried.github.io/blog/sequence-viz</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A collection of visualization tools for exploring sequences of events
over time. Offers the first open-source, Javascript implementation of
Krist Wongsuphasawat&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.cs.umd.edu/hcil/lifeflow/">LifeFlow</a>
for temporal summary visualization as well as extensions and related
techniques.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>After cloning, remember to run</p>

<pre><code>git submodule init
git submodule update
</code></pre>

<p><a href="http://sigfried.org/lifeflow/lifeflowWithStuff.html">LifeFlow demo</a></p>

<p><a href="http://sigfried.org/lifeflow/hurricaneLifeflowUnadorned.html">LifeFlow stripped down demo</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Merki]]></title>
    <link href="http://Sigfried.github.io/blog/merki/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-27T00:03:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://Sigfried.github.io/blog/merki</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Medication Extraction and Reconciliation Knowledge Instrument.</strong>
A tool for extracting structured medication information from discharge
summaries and other free-text narrative sources, described in this
<a href="http://www.amia.org/amia-awards/annual-conference-awards">award-winning</a>
paper: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2655993/">Extracting Structured Medication Event Information from Discharge Summaries</a> by
Sigfried Gold, Noémie Elhadad, Xinxin Zhu, James J. Cimino, and George Hripcsak.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?cites=12861617034331125757&amp;as_sdt=20000005&amp;sciodt=0,21&amp;hl=en">Citations</a>
where you may find more effective parsers built more recently. If you
learn of any that are also open source, let me know!</p>

<h3>MERKI Parser, Public Version, Documentation</h3>

<p>Files:</p>

<pre><code>ParseMeds.pm            parser code module
drugParseRules.yaml     parser rules.  can be edited if you understand regular expressions.
druglist.tsv            list of drug names, CUIs and TTY for ingredients and brand names from RxNorm
gpl.txt                 GPL3 license text
parseFromPerl.pl        example of how to call the parser from a Perl script
parseFromShell.pl       command line version.  run like:
                            echo "...tylenol 250mg po daily..." | perl parseFromShell.pl
</code></pre>

<p>MERKI was a sprawling, ambitious application I worked on during my time
as a student of Biomedical Informatics at Columbia University.  It&rsquo;s
purpose was to extract medication information from structured and
free-text patient data, standardize and condense it, and produce a
complete and concise listing of all medications mentioned in each
patient&rsquo;s electronic medical record.  The larger project was never
finished.  The current files are a portable subset that allow the
parsing of narrative clinical text for the extraction of structured
medication information.</p>

<p>The following two lines from parseFromShell.pl show how to use the
parser:</p>

<pre><code>my $drugs = $parser-&gt;twoLevelParse($input, 
    ['drug', 'possibleDrug', 'context'], 
    ['dose', 'route', 'freq', 'prn', 'date']);  
print $parser-&gt;drugsToXML($drugs);
</code></pre>

<p>$parser->twoLevelParser goes over its input twice: once to extract
drugs, possible drugs, and contexts; and a second time to find, within
each drug or possible drug, the dose, route, frequence, prn and dates.
twoLevelParser returns a Perl data structure which can then be passed
to $parser->drugsToXML or $parser->drugsToHTMLTable in order to turn
it into something more directly usable.  Here is an example (taken from
bits of random clinical text, and not meant to be clinically plausible):</p>

<pre><code>unixshell$ echo "Discharge medications: Procardia XL 60 mg p.o. prn for severe wheezing, ferros sulfate 300 mg p.o. b.i.d., Cipro 250 mg p.o. q12hQ" | perl parseFromShell.pl
&lt;drugs&gt;
    &lt;drug&gt;
        &lt;drugName&gt;Procardia XL&lt;/drugName&gt;
        &lt;dose&gt;60 mg&lt;/dose&gt;
        &lt;route&gt;p.o.&lt;/route&gt;
        &lt;prn&gt;prn for severe wheezing&lt;/prn&gt;
        &lt;startChar&gt;23&lt;/startChar&gt;
        &lt;endChar&gt;69&lt;/endChar&gt;
        &lt;textLength&gt;47&lt;/textLength&gt;
        &lt;when&gt;after discharge&lt;/when&gt;
        &lt;context&gt;Discharge meds&lt;/context&gt;
        &lt;surroundingText&gt;discharge medications: [Procardia XL 60 mg p.o. prn for severe wheezing], ferros sulfate 300 mg p.o. b&lt;/surroundingText&gt;
    &lt;/drug&gt;
    &lt;possibleDrug&gt;
        &lt;drugName&gt;ferros sulfate &lt;/drugName&gt;
        &lt;dose&gt;300 mg&lt;/dose&gt;
        &lt;route&gt;p.o.&lt;/route&gt;
        &lt;freq&gt;b.i.d.&lt;/freq&gt;
        &lt;startChar&gt;72&lt;/startChar&gt;
        &lt;endChar&gt;104&lt;/endChar&gt;
        &lt;textLength&gt;33&lt;/textLength&gt;
        &lt;when&gt;after discharge&lt;/when&gt;
        &lt;context&gt;Discharge meds&lt;/context&gt;
        &lt;surroundingText&gt;p.o. prn for severe wheezing, [ferros sulfate 300 mg p.o. b.i.d.], D1DDD 250 mg p.o. q12hq&lt;/surroundingText&gt;
    &lt;/possibleDrug&gt;
    &lt;drug&gt;
        &lt;drugName&gt;Cipro&lt;/drugName&gt;
        &lt;dose&gt;250 mg&lt;/dose&gt;
        &lt;route&gt;p.o.&lt;/route&gt;
        &lt;freq&gt;q12&lt;/freq&gt;
        &lt;startChar&gt;107&lt;/startChar&gt;
        &lt;endChar&gt;127&lt;/endChar&gt;
        &lt;textLength&gt;21&lt;/textLength&gt;
        &lt;when&gt;after discharge&lt;/when&gt;
        &lt;context&gt;Discharge meds&lt;/context&gt;
        &lt;surroundingText&gt;s sulfate 300 mg p.o. b.i.d., [Cipro 250 mg p.o. q12]hq&lt;/surroundingText&gt;
    &lt;/drug&gt;
&lt;/drugs&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>To understand how the parser decides what counts as a drug, a possible
drug, a context, a dose, route, etc., look at these tokens in
drugParseRules.yaml.  The parser itself (ParseMeds.pm) treats context
tokens differently than drugs and possible drugs.  Any context token
found becomes  the context attribute of all drugs and possible drugs
following it, until another context is found.</p>

<p>Notice that &ldquo;ferros sulfate&rdquo; (&ldquo;ferrous sulfate&rdquo; misspelled) appears as
a possible drug rather than as a drug.  Since it is misspelled, it is
not found in the drug lexicon, but it is still identified as a possible
drug because it appears before a dose, route, and frequency.  (Look at
the definition of possibleDrug in drugParseRules.yaml.)</p>

<p>This application is far from perfect, and if you do find it worth using,
there is a good chance you will want to modify it for your own uses.</p>

<p>Changing the drug lexicon should be fairly straightforward.  You can
add, delete, or change entries as you like, or use an entirely different
lexicon.  If you change the format of the lexicon, you may need to
change aspects of the parser that load and look up drugs.</p>

<p>You may want to change the parsing rules to catch drug phrases that the
current set of rules won&rsquo;t catch, or, alternatively, to make the rules
more conservative to prevent false positives.  You&rsquo;ll need to understand
the basics of the YAML format (or just follow the example of the current
drugParseRules.yaml file), and, more importantly, you&rsquo;ll need to
understand Perl regular expressions and the special way that the parsing
rules are processed.  I&rsquo;ll explain how the parsing rules are processed
now.</p>

<p>Tokens are divided into terminals and non-terminals.  Tokens of either
sort are transformed by the parser into single Perl regular expressions.
The difference is that non-terminals can include terminals and other
non-terminals in their definition.  You&rsquo;ll also notice that the way they
are written is slightly different, but that is just to make them more
readable.  Also, terminals can include literal text, but non-terminals
cannot (because they try to interpret literal text as a reference to
another token.)</p>

<p>Terminals are made up of a name followed by a list of expressions or
pieces of literal text.  Take, for instance, the terminal cond:</p>

<pre><code>cond:   [ud, ut dict, prm-breakthrough, '(were|was) held', discontinued, "dc'd"]
</code></pre>

<p>This will be converted into the (approximately) following regular expression:</p>

<pre><code>/(ud|ut dict|prn-breakthrough|(were|was) held|discontinued|dc\'d)/
</code></pre>

<p>Actually, two other options will be added to the list of strings it will
match: &ldquo;u.d.&rdquo; and &ldquo;ut dict.&rdquo;  This is because the convenience rule
dotsAfterLtrOk includes &ldquo;ud&rdquo; and the convenience rule dotsAtEndOk
includes &ldquo;ut dict&rdquo;.</p>

<p>The terminal cond is used in the non-terminal prn:</p>

<pre><code>- name: prn
  patterns:
    - 'asNeeded\s*qualifier'
    - '(cond|asNeeded)'
</code></pre>

<p>This translates into &ldquo;prn&rdquo; or &ldquo;as needed&rdquo; (that&rsquo;s how &ldquo;asNeeded&rdquo; is
defined) followed by a qualifier (something like &ldquo;for severe pain&rdquo;), OR
something that matches the cond token, OR something that matches the
asNeeded token.  Generally you will see the parsing rules composed
such that more specific, longer expressions appear before less specific,
shorter expressions.  This is because the first expression matched will
be kept and subsequent expressions will not be tried.</p>

<p>Finally, you may also want to modify the parsing code itself, but that
code is not documented and may be hard to understand.</p>

<p>If you do make changes, or even if you use the code at all, I would very
much appreciate hearing from you.  I may be able to offer assistance,
and I may be able to make your improvements available to others.</p>

<p>Contact <a href="http://sigfried.org">Sigfried Gold</a> with questions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
